{"tossups": [{"question": "This man\u2019s alleged last words were \u201cThe battle is at its height - wear my armor and beat my war drums. Do not announce my death.\u201d After his death, this man was given the title Chunmugong. A double agent plot led to the removal of this man in favor of a commander who was decisively defeated at the Battle of Chilchonryang. This man was killed during his final victory at the Battle of Noryang, after he defeated 330 Japanese ships with 13 at the Battle of Myeongnyang. For the point, name this \u201cNelson of the East\u201d, a Korean admiral who championed turtle ships.", "answer": "<b> Yi</b> Sun-Sin", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An early form of this theory was proposed by Girolamo Fracastoro, who termed objects like clothes and linen \u201cfomites.\u201d In one experiment that helped demonstrate this theory, swan neck flasks that were set over a flame and then tilted or had their necks removed had cloudy nutrient broth. Koch\u2019s [coke\u2019s] Postulates stipulate aspects of this theory, which replaced spontaneous generation and miasma theory. For the point, name this theory developed in part by Louis Pasteur which holds that infectious microbial pathogens can cause disease.", "answer": "<b> Germ</b> theory of disease", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "This meeting marked the beginning of a period of civil rights restrictions known as the Conservative Order. Prussia received the Grand Duchy of Posen to prevent Russia from becoming too powerful during this meeting. Ferdinand IV was restored as king of Sicily as a result of this meeting, ousting Marshal Joachim Murat. The Earl of Clancarty led the British delegation at this meeting after Wellington left to fight the Hundred Days. The Concert of Europe was established in, for the point, what meeting chaired by Klemens von Metternich following the Napoleonic Wars?", "answer": "<b> Congress of Vienna</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this region, the Bezeklik Thousand Buddha Cave was built by the Qocho kingdom near Gaochang. Yaqub Beg played a crucial role in launching the Dungan revolt from this region. During the 1750s, an uprising led by Amursana Emperor Qianlong to \u201cpacify\u201d this region, wiping out almost 80% of its Dzungar population. After Sheng Shicai was ousted as governor, the East Turkestan Republic was established in this region. In 1997, Uyghur [we-gur] separatist groups bombed Urumqi [oo-room-chi], the capital of, for the point, what predominantly-Muslim region in northwest China?", "answer": "<b> Xinjiang</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This author criticized war in an ekphrastic work that imagined \u201can artificial wilderness/and a sky like lead\u201d where \u201ca ragged urchin, aimless and alone\u201d assumes \u201cthat girls are raped, that two boys knife a third.\u201d Another work by this author criticizes the Treaty of Versailles by stating \u201cI and the public know/what all schoolchildren learn,/those to whom evil is done/do evil in return.\u201d That poem is set \u201cas the clever hopes expire/of a low dishonest decade\u201d in \u201cone of the dives/on Fifty-Second Street.\u201d For the point, name this poet of<em> The Shield of Achilles</em> and \u201cSeptember 1, 1939\u201d", "answer": "Wystan Hugh<b> Auden</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s trial resulted in the development of the \u201cjoint criminal enterprise\u201d doctrine to prosecute him. This leader was charged with the kidnap and murder of his predecessor, Ivan Stambolic. After refusing to concede an election to Vojislav Kostunica, this man was arrested in the Bulldozer Revolution. This man died of a heart attack in 2006 before a verdict could be reached on his war crimes trial at the Hague, which included charges of deporting and murdering ethnic Albanians in Kosovo. For the point, identify this leader of Serbia during the Yugoslav Wars.", "answer": "Slobodan<b> Milosevic</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One document written for this event declared \u201cdespotism and arbitrariness are suffocating us, we are gasping for breath\u201d and demanded measures against the poverty and ignorance of the people. This event was organized after a strike at the Putilov Ironworks. Unrest following this event led to the establishment of the Duma and the adoption of the October Manifesto. The victims of this event were led by Father Gapon on a march to the Winter Palace. For the point, name this 1905 massacre of peaceful demonstrators by troops loyal to Tsar Nicholas II.", "answer": "<b> Bloody Sunday</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man established a military alliance known as the \u201cnew emerging forces,\u201d or NEFO, to counteract Western influence. After this man invaded West Irian, he signed the New York Accords to make peace with the Netherlands. This man declared independence alongside Mohammed Atta and implemented a system of \u201cGuided Democracy.\u201d This man fell from power after the 30th of September coup was blamed upon his PKI party, which was replaced by the New Order, led by Suharto. For the point, identify this first president of Indonesia.", "answer": "<b> Sukarno</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name the last Shah of Iran.", "answer": "Mohammad Reza<b> Pahlavi</b> (accept Mohammad<b> Reza Shah</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This civilization\u2019s literacy is possibly demonstrated by glyphs on the Cascajal Block, which are unlike the Isthmian script, also called the \u201cEpi-[this civilization]\u201d script. Jade masks found near this civilization\u2019s city of El Manati contain traces of their \u201cwere-jaguar\u201d art motif. This Mesoamerican civilization was the first to practice ritual bloodletting and play the ball game, according to artifacts found near their cities like San Lorenzo and La Venta. For the point, identify this earliest known Mesoamerican culture, which constructed large stone heads.", "answer": "<b> Olmec</b> Civilization Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One speech about this event claims that it was made possible by \u201cfalse statements and expressions for hope of a continued peace.\u201d The decision to carry out this event was taken when a prime minister declared \u201cthis is an ultimatum\u201d after receiving the Hull Note. This event\u2019s planner claimed \u201cI can run wild for six months [after this event]\u201d but did not expect to defeat the Pacific Fleet. December 7 was declared a \u201cdate that will live in infamy\u201d by President Roosevelt after, for the point, what surprise attack in which Japan attacked a Hawaii naval base?", "answer": "Attack on<b> Pearl Harbor</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "According to Henry Charles Lea, victims of this institution were marched in processions accompanied by familiares while wearing sambenito tunics. Benito Garcia was killed by this institution for supposedly tearing out the heart of the Holy Child of La Guardia. This institution conducted auto-da-f\u00b4e ceremonies where they burned marranos and moriscos. This institution was led by a man who advocated for the expulsion of the Jews through the Alhambra Decree, Tomas de Torquemada. For the point, name this fanatical institution which persecuted heretics in an Iberian country.", "answer": "<b> Spanish Inquisition</b> (prompt on just \u201cInquisition\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2013 in this country, referee Ot\u00b4avio Jord\u02dcao da Silva was quartered and beheaded by fans after da Silva fatally stabbed a player in an amateur soccer game. This country carried out a campaign to prevent its<em> torcidas organizadas</em>, gangs of lower-class soccer supporters, from being visibly violent at the Arruda stadium in Recife, the Maracan\u02dca, or its 10 other venues for a 2014 sporting event that included a 7-1 semifinal loss for this country to Germany. Fernandinho and Neymar play for, for the point, what country that hosted the 2014 FIFA World Cup?", "answer": "<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This river was once known as Okeanos Potamos, in which the island of Leuke supposedly contained Achilles\u2019 tomb. A series of defenses on this river include those named for Moesia and Pannonia, and are called Limes [lie-mes]. Following the Treaty of Kucuk Kaynarka, a term was coined referring to principalities on this river that included Wallachia and Moldavia. Apollodorus of Damascus built a bridge across this river for Trajan to invade Dacia. Originating in the Black Forest, for the point, what European river flows through Vienna and Budapest on its way to the Black Sea?", "answer": "<b> Danube</b> River", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "As he is fleeing Buyeo, Jumong is aided by turtles to perform this action. Urshanabi builds an object with \u201cstone things\u201d to perform this action, but Gilgamesh destroys it before their journey to Utnapishtim. Modgudr guards one site used for this action, which Hermodr does to retrieve Baldr from Hel. In the <em>Divine Comedy</em>, Phlegyas helps Virgil and Dante with this action, and Jason loses a sandal while doing this with Hera on his back. Charon is offered a coin to help dead souls with, for the point, what action that Julius Caesar performed over the Rubicon?", "answer": "<b> crossing</b> a<b> river</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s plans were leaked to Henry Wilson by Hugh Forbes which resulted in him losing contact with his Canadian allies. Heyward Shepherd was killed by troops led by this man, an action used by Lost Cause advocates to combat his legacy. The Secret Six funded this man who had earlier received support from William Lloyd Garrison. This man was aided by \u201cGeneral Tubman\u201d who was unable to join him in an attack in Virginia. For the point, name this abolitionist who led a raid on Harpers Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Due to the popularity of governor James Wright, this American colony was the only one of the original thirteen to use the revenue stamps required by the Stamp Act. Slavery was originally banned in this colony as its founder thought it would weaken its status as a buffer against Spanish Florida. James Oglethorpe founded, for the point, what debtors\u2019 haven originally run from Savannah?", "answer": "<b> Georgia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Treaty of Fort Stanwix used this river to establish a new boundary between the British colonies and the Six Nations. Slaves often referred to this river as the \u201cRiver Jordan\u201d as they attempted to cross it with the help of the Underground Railroad. This river set the southern boundary of the Northwest Territory. This river is formed by the confluence of the Monongahela and Allegheny rivers. The Mississippi meets up with this river in Cairo [kay-roh], Illinois. Louisville lies on, for the point, what river that separates Kentucky from its namesake state?", "answer": "<b> Ohio</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The Camelots du Roi often rallied around a statue of this person, an anti-Dreyfusard symbol, in the Place des Pyramides. This person was canonized in 1920 with Th\u00b4erese of Lisieux after their popularity with soldiers in WWI. Jean de Metz led this person\u2019s group of companions provided by Robert de Baudricourt to escort this person to Chinon. This person was tried by Pierre Cauchon after helping lift the Siege of Orl\u00b4eans in the service of Charles VII. For the point, name this peasant girl who was burned at the stake by the English during the Hundred Years War.", "answer": "<b> Jeanne d\u2019Arc</b> (or<b> Joan of Arc</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "At this battle, John Chester ordered his troops to aim their guns at allied troops to prevent their retreat. Marines at this battle cried out that they \u201chad all lost their father\u201d after Peter Salem killed their commander. In the prelude to this battle, British forces advanced on the Dorchester Neck leading Israel Putnam to prepare nearby defenses. Breed\u2019s Hill was the central site of, for the point, what pyrrhic British victory where the order \u201cdo not fire until you see the whites of their eyes\u201d may have been given?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Bunker Hill</b> Page 7", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Saudi Arabia and the United Kingdom supported opposite sides in this country\u2019s Jebel Akhdar War. This country\u2019s southern Dhofar province was the site of a Marxist insurgency led by PFLOAG in the 1960s. This nation\u2019s current leader overthrew his father, Said bin Taimur, in 1970 and is the longest serving Arab leader. In 1861, Lord Canning declared the Sultanate of Zanzibar as independent from this country. Sultan Qaboos rules, ftp what Arabian country whose capital of Muscat served as a trading port on its namesake gulf?", "answer": "<b> Oman</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}